[SPEAKER_00]: Bhante, my mind exhibits such a persistent inclination towards seeking structure and order.
[SPEAKER_00]: I delight in having a to-do list and specific goals as a constant source of motivation and security.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I don't have such things and instead have chaos, I cannot even keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that this is somehow a problem because I should be able to stay steady without structure and despite the chaos.
[SPEAKER_00]: Please help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, eventually, but you can stay steady despite the chaos, but until then, structure can help you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, obviously, it's what you take that structure to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it just like mindless adhering to the observed norm and requirements of your behavior?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it the structure of structuring your day so that you can watch your intentions correctly, not resort to coping mechanisms, meditation techniques, but instead actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Study the suttas in a systematic manner, so that you can then apply that with some discipline around your day-to-day activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that structure is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no problem there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, of course, you know, and you would be recognizing that, if you start applying it rightly, you would also then begin to see that you shouldn't be depending on the structures,
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean that you can't benefit from them initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, oh, I have not developed my mind yet, but I recognize that I shouldn't depend on structures, so I'll just expose myself to absolute chaotic environment, because I shouldn't be moved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you shouldn't be moved if you would have completed development of the mind, for which certain structure is required.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradual training is a form of structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you don't do first, what you don't do second, what you do third, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes gradual development, which is already a form of structuring your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if by structure you mean you need a daily routine, that's programmed hour by hour, and somebody telling you what to do, well, then, yeah, you have to abandon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is a way to... Well, basically, it does not translate to the real world.
[SPEAKER_01]: When sickness and aging and death and loss of the loved ones set in, your kind of micro-managed environment in which you were able to practice your mindfulness and so on, where everything was controlled minute by minute, that does not translate, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be struggling to remain unmoved, because that environment requires quite a wide basis of maintenance, where nothing should go wrong in many different areas, so that you can afford...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically a privileged environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you won't have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... if, eh... if you only know how to practice in that type of protected environment, you don't know how to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, there are layers to the structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a structure somebody policing my every move and telling me to stop or do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it a structure of a gradual training?
[SPEAKER_01]: Both can be called structures, but they are obviously on very different levels.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, one set of structure is very controlling, too controlling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not... that's really not the main issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: The main issue is that the former set, the set of structure where everything is, like, micromanaged and ordered minute by minute, is a structure that's rooted in avoidance of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to think for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to endure the doubt for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to wonder what should I do next.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just give it to me written, set in stone, on paper, the weight of the authority and I'll just adhere to it because it's easier.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that structure is a structure of the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your structure is structured around your daily activities to support your taking up responsibility and sense restraint and withdrawal from the unwholesome states, that's a fine, that's a fine structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you got to be doing it yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not relying on the world to force it upon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not relying on the world to force it upon you, or to do it for you, taking up the burden of the action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, I suppose, a person will want to, like, find a teacher, which is a good thing, who will tell me what to do, and I will submit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to find a teacher, so you can learn from, so that you can apply those things yourself, for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, for many people, finding a teacher equals finding an external authority to which I'll commit, so I don't have to think for myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a... that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: The core of that type of structure is avoiding responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is a... that is a prerequisite for successful practice of dhamma, to have to take responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter how much effort you invest subsequently upon that structure, in terms of practice, you actually killed it at its roots.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no responsibility at that fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to revert all the way back, abandon it, and then restart.